So there are these two views the view of
being and the view of non-being
and the suta say that anyone who relies
on the view of being will be opposed to
the view of non-being
>> and anyone who relies on the view of
non-being will be opposed to the view of
being. >> Mhm. Then it says, "One who does not
>> Mhm. Then it says, "One who does not
understand as it really is the origin,
disappearance, gratification, danger and
escape in the case of being and
non-being, is affected by lust, hatred
and delusion and dwells in suffering."
>> So I wonder what is meant by being and
non-being here and what is the
gratification, danger and escape.
>> Mhm.
Well, in the in the broadest terms, um,
being is that which is anything that is,
anything that can be discerned,
perceived, thought about, anything that
exists, that is what being is.
that is what being is.
So, you could have like a, you know, you
could perceive specific things and there
is a form of being that which you're
perceiving. But then you could also
start perceiving more general things
such as your experience of perception.
You could discern that and that also
exists and that is also a form of being. So
and that is also a form of being. So
being is not like a static
scientifically measured thing on account
of on the basis of your um senses. It's
anything that can be mentally discerned
as is including mentality as well. So if
if if there is a sense of doesn't matter
how vague or how abstract it might feel
it's real as such that's often say and
the reality of that say abstract thought
of being that somebody might have in the
beginning uh that reality of that
experience of thinking abstract thoughts
of being is real as such and that is
already a form of being that is already
a form of existence
so when the Buddha talks about a being
he doesn't talk about specific instances
um or manifestations of that being. He
talks about the whole nature of your
experience that has it that's already a
form of being because it exists in a
certain way. You know the five
aggregates the whole the uh the
experience as a whole and so on. So
fundamentally uh on those most general like
uh on those most general like
fundamental levels uh people will either
be um
adhering to the being or or trying to
get rid of it, trying to deny it.
So um
and like say for example like you might
be specifically say I I I don't like
this. So you might be specifically
trying to get rid of that particular
being, particular type of existence that
you're experiencing. You want to modify
it. You want to change it. But overall,
you're very much still enamored and
infatuated with the state of existence,
with the nature of it. Broadly speaking,
you are not um you you are very much
delighting in that
in your own existence as a whole. Like
you have no issue with it. But then you
could have people that basically start
finding issue with that with their sense
of existence as a whole. While on a
particular level they might not be
against things but their general view
it's like they relish the non-being.
They delight in the absence of it when
when when it occurs and so on. So in
other words, either way you're bound by
that broadest sense of being of your
existence like the five aggregates the
the the framework of your experience. Um
so that's why like those who
fundamentally delight in their own
existence in their own isness so to
speak in the in the broadest sense they
will be opposed to any idea of oh this
will come to an end
um this will expire this could be
destroyed so basically when that being if if that
so basically when that being if if that
being were to change or cease they would
be opposed to that they would not be
feel they won't feel that pleasantly
basically they would feel threatened by
it and same those who for whatever
reason relish the idea oh I don't care
because everything you know including
myself will come to an end and that's
that's that will be the finish so
there's nothing to worry about anyway
well if they were told that well
actually that won't be the end the being
will continue just maybe in another form
they don't relish that idea because they
find solace and freedom well freedom not
really freedom but they find solace and
comfort and safety in the idea said that
doesn't matter how bad it is, it's going
to come to an end and ever after there
will be no more problems when the being
ends. That's just complete annihilation
and it's the finishing of everything.
Um, but either way, what they don't
realize that doesn't matter how hard you
think about annihilation and the absence
of the being in the most general sense,
that experience in of itself, it's a
form of being because it can be
discerned and it is in that way.
So you're not escaping the being.
Doesn't matter how much you try to
destroy it.
So that's like the whole point is to
discern whether you are relishing
finding safety in the existence
or looking forward for it when it ends
because you you have conflated that with
the idea of oh you'll be free ever after
there will be no more problems. Um
either way you're bound with the being.
So either way basically you are you are
u you're mistaken
and um and that the whole middle way
it's basically recognizing that whether
you think existence whether you think
non-existence that experience is real as
such for you there and then and that
thing is that experience is which means
you can't just you won't be able to um
free yourself and overcome
being simply through falling into a view
that everything is or everything will
not be.
Because you're bound by being not
through simply thinking this or that,
but through your constant interaction
on the basis of your existence with
other further kind of forms and shapes
and manifestations of that existence of
the five agriates and those interactions
are always fueled by greed, lust,
aversion. So for as long as you are
acting out of those bases, you are
maintaining your Baba. Whether you want
it or not, whether you want to deny it,
whether you believe it will end, whether
you believe it will last forever, all of
those beliefs are pretty much the
results of your engagement with your own
sense of being through passion, through
aversion, through uh appropriation, through
through uh appropriation, through
acquisition and all of that. So yes,
being is a problem because you're not
like your own being is a problem because
like oh I am but I'm not my own. I'm not
in my own control. Whichever way things
decide to go, my control can only
prevent it only so far. There's always
going to be a line where things will be
out of my hands and my kind of my
existence will be at the mercy of that.
So being is a problem. But then like
whether you hold the view that well
being being is not a problem or being is
a problem and when it ends I'll be free
from the problem you're still
maintaining it because you're still
basically connected with it through your
own actions and through your own
ignorance. So that's that whole kind of
the the standard description of
understanding the gratification, danger
and the escape in regard to being. In
other sutas, the Buddha said in regard
to sensuality in regard to four
elements, it was the same description.
In other words, it's the description
that basically means discerning the
middle ground. So discerning what the
real problem is. The problem is not that
I find safety in the being. The problem
is not that I hate the being and I want
it to end or believe that that would be
my freedom and then I find safety in
that. The problem is that either of
those views are the results of my
passionate involvement with the being
that I am there and then when I think
those things.
So then if you address it on that level
both this kind of eternalist and
annihilationist fundamental kind of
standpoints as the sorts talk about them
will disappear. You wouldn't have to be
sort of counterarguing and reasoning
your way out because you would have
removed uh that wrongful basis that you
wrongful connection, wrongful
relationship that you have with your own
existence. A relationship of passion,
ill will, distraction and so on and then
basically being will not be anymore
owned by you assumed through your own
actions uh of the wrong kind. So then whether
uh of the wrong kind. So then whether
that being exists or when currently or
where it's going to end either way you
won't be affected by it because you
escaped it and you escape it by
recognizing the danger of finding safety
in it.
But see that's not enough just aha okay
so being is dangerous therefore being
free from being is better. But unless
you actually start tailoring your
actions accordingly to those
reflections, you're just going to fall
into a view of blaming the being for
your problems. Blaming your existence
for the problems and then thinking when
the existence ends, all the problems
will end.
But yeah, being is a problem if you're
infatuated with it. But then if you just
start to deny it, you are still not
changing the problem. You're still under
its thumb, so to speak. So that's why
it's like okay yeah being infatuated
with the being is is bad denying the
being won't free you from that either.
So what do I do? Well that's what the
Buddha recognized. Okay so I recognize
why am I intoxicated with the being? Why
am I losing perspective of my actions
towards sensuality towards this towards
that out of passion aversion? Oh, it's
because it's like carelessness here and
now. I don't see the benefit of
withdrawing from it and I don't
recognize the connection between those
actions and the problem of my existence.
So that's the whole the Buddhist
teaching explaining that in so many
ways. And then the more you start to
recognize then it becomes apparent that
oh yeah the only reason you were
engaging with it is because it was
providing you with a sense of safety.
Same with sensuality
u providing a form of escape from
discomfort from uneasiness and so on. So
but unless you first renounce that as a
form of escape you won't find the the
the the more adequate form of escape
because they're kind of the opposite
directions. So you can either go left or
right. You can't go left and right at
the same time. So then the whole danger
gratification well gratification means
that like aha I engage with this because
it offers me this superficial safety
that I don't look past and I'm
intoxicated with it. What's the danger?
Well the danger is that it's not really
safety. Someone says come in this is a
safe house. You're safe here. And you
might feel safe initially and then you
recognize oh no this was a trap.
Actually in this safe house I am at
their mercy.
And then you wouldn't lose a second of
trying to leave that place when you
recognize the true danger. So that's
like knowing the danger, knowing the
gratification, which then if you fully
understand will result in finding the
escape because the only reason people don't
because the only reason people don't
find escape out of their own existence
from their own existence is because they
still think they are uh in a in a place
of safety. They still don't see the
danger of staying there. So like how
could they possibly find a way out when
they don't even look for it?
So now a sotapana understands
the origin of suffering as craving for
sensual pleasures and also as craving
for being and non-being. So can we say
that the craving for sensual pleasure is
still on the level of more particular
things but the craving for being and
non-being some some more general layer
he has also understood.
>> Yeah. Well, so the one understands that
craving is the root of suffering. He
might not initially be understanding the
implications of oh the layers so to
speak of oh craving for sensuality,
craving for being, craving for
non-being. He knows the craving is a is
an issue. That's where the suffering
that's where the suffering comes from.
It doesn't come from things. It doesn't
come from the absence of things. Comes
from you craving for pleasure, craving
away from pain and so on. So if he then
pursues his own understanding of craving
is a problem. I if he pursues the
development of the four noble truths
like the sutas talk about then he gets
to realize that yeah he basically your
starting position is the domain of
sensuality that's why sautapan is still
not free from sensual desires so he
understood craving to be the problem but
he hasn't diminished it sufficiently
enough for that domain of sensuality to
to kind of evaporate to disappear so for
somebody who is not free from sensuality
there's really no craving for being or
non-being that they can discern because
any form of uh affirmation or
resistance, eternalism or annihilationism will be
eternalism or annihilationism will be
well within the kama, the being of
sensuality. That's their domain. That's
where the mind operates. That's where
their craving is very much still engaged
with. But say then you make the effort
not giving into that craving uh
contemplating the danger and so on. And
that craving by not being fed will
eventually dissipate and then you would
have lost say
uh interest in the sense objects because
you recognize that the only reason you
were seeking and pursuing interest in
sense objects is because you believe
that's where the safety was coming from.
Then what's left for you will be that
batana envatana
craving for presence craving for absence
and so on. And that's kind of the the
level of of anagami in the sutras
like in terms of the the development
towards kind of um overcoming the degree
of craving. Then what's left is like
yeah Anagam is somebody he still might
have some internal leaning of their
chitta towards the presence of a certain
experiences and the absence of a certain
experiences like I prefer if this were
and I prefer if this weren't. But
obviously at no point will those
leanings be able to become what they
used to be like a full-on blown desire
towards sense objects as forms of escape
from what's being pressuring you here
and now.
>> And is this what is meant by the conceit
I am?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Like that's but conceited I
am would be corresponding to Yeah. those
subtler cravings that that would have
been left. Yeah.
And how does an anagami practice in
order to abandon even that conceit and
attain the complete freedom? Same same.
So when he starts to recognize those
subtler leanings that factually like
from the point of view of puja obviously
but even from the point of view of
sautapana from the point of view of like
even like sakagami somebody who is
already weakened those things you could
factually say that those leanings are
not even an issue.
like there's there's virtually no
suffering involved. It's just almost
like on the level of agreeable
disagreeable. That's why like often in the sutas
That's why like often in the sutas
uh anagamis would think they were arros.
Often the Buddha would say when they
were asked like, "Oh, are all these
arans?" They declared arahanship. Are
they all aran? Says, "Well, I could tell
like half of them are but half of them
overestimated themselves." But they were
factually like anagamies at least. And
even the Buddha himself often would say
practice like this and it would result
in complete aranchip
unless there is some residues left in
which case state of non return because
obviously things get a lot subtler and
there might be some residues that don't
even show up so to speak but the
practice remains the same. So for an
anagami like he just needs to recognize
that there could be residual
implications of these mental innings and
he doesn't need to I must stop this. No,
he just needs to regain the same context
that brought him there. In other words,
start including those little
preferential kind of almost automatic
leaning away, leaning towards that do
not induce any measure of craving. But
he includes even that as a possible
basis for craving. So he contemplates
the same gratification danger that then
results in not even um losing
perspective in regard to those subtler
things and that's where there will be no
conceit left.
So same same same same kind of uh same
kind of practice just um like on account
of
uh
little faith so to speak
anagami can then just out of faith even
start including
things that do not as I said are not
problem by any measure by any any kind
of uh comparison to craving but just in
case, he would still practice the same
he would still practice the same
context, maintenance, recollection of
the same context, contemplating of the
danger because again, he has nothing to
lose by doing that. He can only gain.
And if he's already an arant, well,
again, he's just confirming what he
already is. He's just aligning what what
what his existence already is.